<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<Document xmlns:gate="http://www.gate.ac.uk" name="A24_F04_FlowFixer_Using_BFECC_for_Fluid_Simulation_SUMMARY_v1.xml">


  
    f8ecf34c6738231f7f30a7e564bb73c1f9b7434e9bbc5cad3cb3a160eab9c904
    3x7q
    http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/1275808.1276500
  
  
    
      Eurographics <CitSpan>Workshop on Natural Phenomena (2005)</CitSpan> E. Galin, P. Poulin (Editors)
      
        <Title>FlowFixer: Using BFECC for Fluid Simulation</Title>
      
      
        
          ByungMoon Kim Yingjie Liu Ignacio Llamas Jarek Rossignac
        
      
      Georgia Institute of Technology
      <Abstract>
<Sentence inAbstract="true">Back and Forth Error Compensation and Correction (BFECC) was recently developed for interface computation by using the level set method.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="true">We show that it can be applied to reduce dissipation and diffusion encountered in various advection steps in fluid simulation such as velocity, smoke density and image advections.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="true">BFECC can be implemented easily on top of the first order upwinding or semi-Lagrangian integration of advection equations, while providing second order accuracy both in space and time.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="true">When applied to level set evolution, BFECC reduces volume loss significantly.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="true">We combine these techniques with variable density projection and show that they yield a realistic animations of two-phase flows.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="true">We demonstrate the benefits of this approach on the image advection and on the simulation of smoke, of bubbles in water, and of a highly dynamic interaction between water, a solid, and air.</Sentence>
</Abstract>
    
    
      
        <H1>1. Introduction</H1>
      
      <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">Simulation of incompressible fluid involves several computation steps including diffusion, advection and pressure projection.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">Advection steps transport some quantities from one region to another along the fluid’s velocity field.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="5.00">In this paper, we explore four forms of advection encountered in fluid simulation: velocity, smoke density, image and level set advections.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.67">Velocity advection transports the velocity field along the velocity itself.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">This step is always needed in nonsteady flow simulation based on Navier-Stokes equation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">Smoke density advection transports smoke along the velocity field.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">Sometimes, we may want to advect a colored image, which may be considered as colored smoke.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">We call this process image advection.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">When one uses a level set method <CitSpan>[OS88]</CitSpan> to simulate a free surface or a two-phase flow, for example a water surface simulation, the level set must be transported as well.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">We call it level set advection.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">Those advection steps can be computed by an upwind or a semi-Lagrangian method.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">The latter is often preferred due to its stability for large time step.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">The first order semi-Lagrangian method is popular in computer animation because of its simplicity.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">However, the first order semiLagrangian contains a significant amount of numerical diffusion and dissipation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">In velocity advection, it yields damped fluid motion.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">In smoke density advection, it leads to a premature dilution of smoke, and is not able to simulate pure advec- tion.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">Therefore, higher order schemes, such as WENO or CIP [ TFK ∗ 03 ], are desired.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="4.67">We show that the implementation complexity of these schemes may be easily avoided by adding a very simple Back and Forth Error Compensation and Correction (BFECC) to an existing first order semiLagrangian schemes, thus improving its space and time accuracy to second order.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="4.67">We show that this approach reduces velocity damping and smoke density dilution and demonstrate its benefits on the four forms of advections discussed previously.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">BFECC was recently proposed in <CitSpan>[DL03, DL04]</CitSpan> as a level set interface computation method.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">As is mentioned in <CitSpan>[ELF05]</CitSpan>, high order methods may not prevent volume loss much.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">However, the authors of <CitSpan>[DL03]</CitSpan> combined BFECC with their simple redistancing technique and applied it to the Zalesak’s problem, showing significantly reduced the volume loss.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">In the level set framework, the one with smallest volume error would be the particle level set method <CitSpan>[EMF02, ELF05]</CitSpan> In this paper, we focus on applying BFECC to velocity and smoke advection steps rather than level set advection.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="4.33">We, however, use BFECC and the simple redistancing for level set advection of various fluid simulations and show that sufficiently realistic fluid animation can be obtained.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">It would be interesting to apply this to the level set advection part of the particle level set method <CitSpan>[ELF05]</CitSpan> for more demanding simulation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">The stability problems in the earlier works such as <CitSpan>[ FM96 ]</CitSpan> were successfully remedied in <CitSpan>[ Sta99 ]</CitSpan> by introducing the pressure projection scheme to enforce incompressibility of the fluid and the semi-Lagrangian treatment of the advection term in the Navier-Stoke equation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">This solution is popular for the simulation of incompressible Fluids, such as smoke <CitSpan>[ FSJ01 ]</CitSpan> and also for more challenging free surface flows <CitSpan>[ FF01 , EMF02 ]</CitSpan>.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">The semi-Lagrangian velocity advection <CitSpan>[Sta99]</CitSpan> comes with built-in dissipation, i.e., the velocity is dissipated quickly since the linear interpolation in the first order semiLagrangian produces large error.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">While higher order interpolation can solve the problem, it involves more neighboring grid point values and increases the complexity, particularly when non-uniform mesh structures are used.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">In <CitSpan>[FSJ01]</CitSpan>, vorticity is added to generate small scale fluid rolling motion.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">Recently, <CitSpan>[ SSK05 ]</CitSpan> addressed this built-in dissipation by enhancing advection itself.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">They adopted the CIP [ TFK ∗ 03 ] method that increases the order of accuracy in space by introducing the derivatives of velocity to build a sub-cell velocity profile.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">A nice feature of this CIP method is that it is local in the sense that only the grid point values of one cell are used in order to update a point value.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">However, in this CIP method, all components of velocity and their partial derivatives should be advected, increasing the implementation complexity and computation time, especially in 3D.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">It is also worth noting that CIP has higher order accuracy in space only.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">Therefore high order integration of characteristics is also necessary.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">In contrast, BFECC is easier to implement and exhibits second order accuracy both in space and time and is local during each of its operational steps.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">Song et al <CitSpan>[ SSK05 ]</CitSpan> focused on applying CIP to generate more dynamic water surface behavior.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">However, we believe that having less dissipative and diffusive advection provides significant benefits in smoke simulations as well.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">This is illustrated in the middle five images of Fig. 4 , where large amount of dissipation makes the smoke look very dark.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">In contrast, when BFECC is used, the smoke keeps full brightness throughout the simulation as is shown in the last five images.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">The introduction of the level set method to fluid animation in <CitSpan>[ FF01 ]</CitSpan> allowed realistic simulation of fluids with complex free surfaces.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">The problem left here was the volume loss in the level set method and the solution, known as the particle level set method, proposed subsequently in <CitSpan>[ EMF02 ]</CitSpan>, turned out to be very successful in volume preservation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">The two phase fluid solver using variable density projection has been broadly studied in mathematics and fluid mechanics [ SSO94 , OKBG00 , HKLS04 ].</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">It has been used in graphics applications by <CitSpan>[ HK03 ]</CitSpan>, where the authors simulated air bubbles rising and merging and by [TFK ∗ 03, SSK05], where splash style interactions between water surface and air are studied.</Sentence>
      c The Eurographics Association 2005.
      ByungMoon Kim &amp; Yingjie Liu &amp; Ignacio Llamas &amp; Jarek Rossignac / FlowFixer: Using BFECC for Fluid Simulation
      2. Previous Work
      3. Fluid Simulation
      
        1
        Consider the following Navier-Stokes equation ∂ ∂ u t = −u · ∇u + ν ∇ · (∇u) − ρ 1 ∇P + f.
      
      <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.00">We follow the operator splitting steps proposed in <CitSpan>[Sta99]</CitSpan> except for the advection step, where we use BFECC and for the projection step for which we use the variable density pressure projection.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.67">We use the standard staggered grid <CitSpan>[FSJ01]</CitSpan>.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Suppose all terms in <CitSpan>(1)</CitSpan> except for − ρ 1 ∇P are treated and let the velocity obtained so far be u.</Sentence>  <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">̃ The final step is applying the variable density pressure projection step to enforce the continuity equation ∇ · u = 0, i.e, solving the equation ∇ · ∆t ρ ∇P = ∇ · u.</Sentence>  <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">̃ Its first order discretization is ∆x ∆t 2 P i, ρ j − i− P 2 1 i−1, , j j + P i, ρ j − i+ P 1 2 i+1, , j j + P i, ρ j − i, j− P i, 2 1 j−1 + P i, ρ j − i, j+ P i, 2 1 j+1 1 = ∆x u  ̃ i+ 2 1 , j − u  ̃ i− 2 1 , j + v  ̃ i, j+ 1 2 − v  ̃ i, j− 1 2 .</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">
<CitSpan>(2)</CitSpan> We assume ∆x = ∆y here and through the rest of the presentation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">The extension to 3D is straightforward and hence omitted.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">This first order approximation is identical to <CitSpan>[ SSK05 ]</CitSpan> and higher order formulations can be found in [ ABS96 , SAB ∗ 99 ].</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Obviously, if ρ is constant, we have the pressure projection ∆t ρ ∇ 2 P = ∇ · u introduced in <CitSpan>[ Sta99 ]</CitSpan>.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">We also include a simple implementation of surface tension similar to [ SAB ∗ 99 ].</Sentence>
      
        <H1>4. The BFECC Method</H1>
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">In this section, we review the BFECC method.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">Since we want to apply it to various advections, we use φ to denote a quantity that is advected and reserve the symbol φ for the level set function through the presentation of this paper.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">This φ can be the velocity components u, v, w, smoke density, RGB color of an image or level set function φ , satisfying</Sentence>
        
          3
          φ t + u · ∇φ = 0.
        
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">We briefly describe the BFECC method here.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Let L be the first order upwinding or semi-Lagrangian integration steps to integrate <CitSpan>(3)</CitSpan>, such that</Sentence>
        
          4
          φ n+1 = L(u, φ n ).
        
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Using this notation, the BFECC can be written as the following three L-calling process</Sentence>
        
          5
          φ n+1 = L u, φ n + 1 φ n − φ  ̄ 2 where φ  ̄ = L (−u, L (u, φ n )) .
        
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">One may understand this method intuitively as follows.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">If the advection step L(·, ·) is exact, the first two forward and backward steps should return the value exactly the same as the original one, i.e., φ n = φ  ̄ .</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">However, this does not hold due to the error in the advection operation L. Suppose L contains an error e.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Then the first two forward and backward steps will produce error 2e, i.e., φ  ̄ = φ n + 2e.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Therefore, the error can be computed as e = − 1 2 ( φ n − φ  ̄ ).</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">We subtract this error e before the final forward advection step.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Then the equation <CitSpan>(5)</CitSpan> becomes φ n+1 = L(u, φ n − e).</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">This step will add an additional e, which will be cancelled by the subtracted amount −e.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">This method is proven to be second order accurate both in space and time <CitSpan>[DL03, DL04]</CitSpan>.</Sentence>
        c The Eurographics Association 2005.
        ByungMoon Kim &amp; Yingjie Liu &amp; Ignacio Llamas &amp; Jarek Rossignac / FlowFixer: Using BFECC for Fluid Simulation
        
          Figure 1: On the right column, a highly dynamic behavior of water interaction with air, air bubbles, and solid is made possible by the two-phase formulation and the BFECCbased reduction of the dissipation in the velocity advection step. On the left column, the BFECC is turned off and the splash is lower.
        
      
      
        <H2>4.1. Implementation of BFECC</H2>
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">In this section, we provide a pseudo code to show the simplicity of the BFECC implementation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">First let the function SingleStep(u, v, φ n , φ n+1 ) implement upwind or semiLagrangian integration of the scalar field φ , which can be the velocity components u,v,w, the smoke density, RGB colors of an image or the level set function φ .</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Then BFECC is implemented as:
        SingleStep(u, v, φ n , φ  ̃ ) SingleStep(−u, −v, φ  ̃ , φ  ̄ ) φ  ̃ := φ n + ( φ n − φ  ̄ )/2 SingleStep(u, v, φ  ̃ , φ n+1 )</Sentence>
        
          Figure 2: Comparison of without (top) and with (bottom) BFECC in velocity advection on a 80×200 grid. Top images show damped fluid motion. Bottom ones show small scale details as well as large scale fluctuations thanks to BFECC applied to the velocity advection step.
        
      
      
        <H2>4.2. BFECC for Velocity Advection</H2>
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">We can use <CitSpan>(5)</CitSpan> to implement the velocity advection step in solving the Navier-Stokes Equation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">In this case, φ becomes u, v and w.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.33">We show that BFECC can improve the damping in the first order semi-Lagrangian implementation of velocity advection, which is a well known drawback of <CitSpan>[Sta99]</CitSpan>.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">For multiphase flow, this BFECC needs to be turned off near the interface to prevent velocities of different fluids with different densities from being mixed, which creates momentum changes.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">We simply turn BFECC off, i.e., use the first order semi-Lagrangian, for the grid points where | φ | &lt; 5∆x.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.67">We also turn it off near the boundary.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">Notice that reducing velocity dissipation is equally important in the entire fluid domain, not only near the interface.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">In other words, turning BFECC off near the interface has little effect since it is still turned on in most of the fluid domain.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">As is shown in Fig. 2 , applying BFECC adds details in smoke motion.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">Notice that these details cannot be obtained from the vorticity confinement method <CitSpan>[FSJ01]</CitSpan>, which only adds small scale rolling motions.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">We also performed the same test in a coarser grid of 100×40.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">In this case, the flow did not fluctuate at all around the obstacles with the first order semi-Lagrangian advection.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">However, when BFECC was added, the flow fluctuated as in the refined grid.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.67">We conclude that BFECC creates a physically correct fluctuations in a coarser grid.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">Velocity advection can also be important when rigid bodies are involved.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">In Fig. 7 , the cup does not tumble due to the velocity dissipation in the first order semi-Lagrangian method, while the cup tumbles when BFECC is applied to the velocity advection step.</Sentence>
        c The Eurographics Association 2005.
        ByungMoon Kim &amp; Yingjie Liu &amp; Ignacio Llamas &amp; Jarek Rossignac / FlowFixer: Using BFECC for Fluid Simulation
        
          Figure 3: Advection of an image along with the up-going flow field on 100×250 grid. The first image shows initial location of the image. The next six images are without BFECC where the dissipation/diffusion are significant. The last six images are with BFECC, where the dissipation is greatly reduced and the features of the image can be identified.
        
        
          Figure 4: Simulation of weakly diffusive and dissipative smoke in bubble rising and bursting situation. The far left image shows the initial bubble. The next five are without BFECC, where the dissipation/diffusion in the semi-Lagrangian step deteriorate the density of smoke. The last five images simulated with BFECC show minimal dissipation/diffusion and the smoke is in full density throughout the simulation. Notice that all simulation parameters are exactly same except for the usage of BFECC in smoke advection. Therefore the only difference is the density of smoke. Also, notice that the simulation time differs by less than 1% since it is dominated by the pressure projection step.
        
      
      
        <H2>4.3. BFECC for Smoke Density and Image Advection</H2>
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.67">We also apply BFECC to the advection of smoke density for the smoke simulation.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">In Fig. 3 and 4, we show that BFECC can reduce dissipation and diffusion significantly.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">As is shown in <CitSpan>[DL03]</CitSpan>, BFECC is linearly stable in l 2 sense, i.e., ||a|| l 2 = ∑ |a i j | 2 is bounded, when the velocity field is constant, where a is the smoke density.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">However, density values a i j can become negative or greater than 1.0 for some grid points.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.67">In our simulation, this problem was not significant and we simply clamped those values to stay in <CitSpan>[0, 1]</CitSpan>.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.00">To measure the diffusion/dissipation amount, we design a test problem similar to Zalesak’s problem.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">Instead of the notched disk, we place a color image and rotate it 360 degree and then compare it with the original image as is shown in Fig. 5 .</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">As is shown in (d), the dissipation of the color is significantly reduced with BFECC.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.00">During the advection, the image is also diffused to neighboring region, even though it is not visible.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">To visualize the diffusion amount, we plot background pixels as blue to show the region where the image has been diffused into.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">As is shown in (d), the color of the object is little diffused into neighboring region when BFECC is used.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">Also notice that the size of the image looks smaller and its position is noticeably different from the original location in (c), which is again fixed in (d) where BFECC is used.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">The computation time was 0.156 sec (without BFECC) and 0.36 sec (with BFECC) per frame on a 3GHz Pentuim4.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">Advection is often used for scientific visualization, especially for various forms of flow visualization.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">For example, <CitSpan>[JEH02]</CitSpan> uses semi-Lagrangian advection of dye to visualize the vector field.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">
<CitSpan>[Wei04]</CitSpan> applied level set method to advect dye without diffusion.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">Only one dye color is allowed and the dye cannot be diffused at all.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">Also level set implementation is needed.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.67">In contrast, BFECC is trivial to implement and provides advection of fully colored pattern of dye, if necessary.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.67">As is shown in Fig. 3 , the dissipation/diffusion is very small.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">Thus, we believe that it can be used in flow visualization as well.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">This remains as a future work.</Sentence>
        
          Figure 5: Test of dissipation and diffusion with image advection problem on a rotating vector field (800×800 grid, CFL = 6.29). (b) is the top center portion of the original image (a). (c) is obtained by rotating it 360 degree using the first order semi-Lagrangian scheme, where one can see large amount of dissipation, diffusion, shrinkage of image and position error. These are significantly improved in (d) where BFECC is used. The blue background region is in fact in black color but it is rendered as blue to illustrate the region where the color is not diffused into.
        
        c The Eurographics Association 2005.
        ByungMoon Kim &amp; Yingjie Liu &amp; Ignacio Llamas &amp; Jarek Rossignac / FlowFixer: Using BFECC for Fluid Simulation
        5. Results
        
          Figure 6: The far left image shows an air bubble placed in olive oil at time zero. The next three images are first order semi-Lagrangian implementation of level set advection. The next three images are produced using BFECC and simple redistancing, showing significantly reduced volume loss.
        
      
      
        <H2>
<H2>4.4. BFECC for Level Set Advection</H2>
</H2>
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.67">Even though, BFECC still has some volume loss in fluid simulation, especially for small droplets or thin filaments, it is still interesting to show how BFECC performs in the fluid simulation since it is trivial to implement and fast.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">When we use the BFECC for level set advection, i.e., φ = φ , redistancing is needed to keep the level set function as a signed distance function.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">We use the following redistancing equation <CitSpan>[SSO94]</CitSpan>
</Sentence>
        
          6
          ∇φ φ τ + w · ∇φ = sgn( φ ) where w = sgn( φ ) |∇ φ | .
        
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">w is the velocity vector for redistancing.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">This equation can be solved by applying first order upwinding in discretizing the term w · ∇φ .</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">An alternative is the semi-Lagrangian style integration, i.e., φ n+1 = φ n (x − w∆ τ ) + sgn( φ n )∆ τ , where x is the location of each grid point.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.33">Hence, φ n (x − w∆ τ ) is the φ value of previous location.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">When these integration formulae for <CitSpan>(6)</CitSpan> are combined with BFECC, the redistancing tends to spoil good φ values computed from the second order accurate BFECC.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">This leads to the idea of turning redistancing off near the interface to keep good φ values there.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">The conditions to turn off redistancing is provided in <CitSpan>[DL03]</CitSpan>, where the significant enhancement were shown for the Zalesak’s problem.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">This simple redistancing is crucial in preserving volume <CitSpan>[DL03]</CitSpan>.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">It is also easy to implement since it simply requires to perform redistancing at the points where at least one of the following two conditions are met.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">• When the grid point is not close to the interface, i.e., when φ i, j has the same sign with its eight neighbors.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">• When the slope is sufficiently high, i.e., when | φ i, j − φ i±1, j | or | φ i, j − φ i, j±1 | ≥ 1.1∆x.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">We test BFECC in different fluid simulations.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="4.00">We simulate air-water and olive oil-air interactions.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Properties of these fluids are provided in Table 1 .</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">Water is rendered as bluish surface and olive oil is rendered in yellowish color.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">We use PovRay ( http://povray.org ) to render images.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">In Fig. 7 , we simulated a cup, air and water interaction.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">The cup is released upside down near the water surface.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">Due to its weight, the cup sinks deep into water but it soon rise again because of the air in it.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.00">However, in the top, we turned BFECC off for velocity advection and hence the water became dissipative, preventing the cup from tumbling.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.00">In the bottom, we use BFECC for velocity advection, where the velocity dissipation is small and hence the cup can tumble 180 degree.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="4.33">This example indicates that reducing velocity dissipation could be important in simulating fluid and rigid body interaction.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.67">We implement the rigid fluid method <CitSpan>[CMT04]</CitSpan> to simulate rigid body and fluid interaction in Fig. 1 and 7.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">We use multiple pressure projections to address the seeping problem mentioned in <CitSpan>[CMT04]</CitSpan>.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.33">The computation time varies in situations such as the complexity of fluid motions.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">In simple bubble rising situation without rigid body, it took a few seconds per time step using a 50 3 mesh.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="2.00">The cup example in Fig. 7 has multiple pressure projections and it took about 30 to 130 seconds per time step on a 70 3 grid.</Sentence>
        
          
            
              
                
                  
                   ρ [kg/m 3 ]
                   ν [m 2 /sec]
                   Surf. Tension [N/m]
                
              
              
                
                   air
                   1.125
                   1.7×10 −5
                  
                
                
                   water
                   1000
                   1.0×10 −6 −5
                   0.07
                
                
                   olive oil
                   910
                   9.2×10
                   0.035
                
              
            
          
          ρ [kg/m 3 ] ν [m 2 /sec] Surf. Tension [N/m] air 1.125 1.7×10 −5 water 1000 1.0×10 −6 0.07 olive oil 910 9.2×10 −5 0.035
          Table 1: Properties of fluids used in simulations
        
      
      
        <H1>6. Conclusion</H1>
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="3.33">We have shown that the BFECC scheme can be used to improve the simulation of fluids.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="4.67">Once the simple first order upwinding or semi-Lagrangian steps for velocity, smoke density, image or level set advections are implemented, BFECC can be added with a trivial amount of code.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="4.67">We show that this simple extension yields significant enhancements in reducing diffusion and dissipation in velocity, smoke, image advection and in preserving volume under various situations including two-phase flows and rigid bodies.</Sentence> <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">The benefits of the proposed approach are illustrated in the accompanying video.</Sentence>
      
      
        <H1>7. Acknowledgement</H1>
        <Sentence inAbstract="false" summaryRelevanceScore="1.0">This work was supported by the NSF under the ITR Digital clay grant 0121663.</Sentence>
        c The Eurographics Association 2005.
        ByungMoon Kim &amp; Yingjie Liu &amp; Ignacio Llamas &amp; Jarek Rossignac / FlowFixer: Using BFECC for Fluid Simulation
        
          Figure 7: Simulation of a sinking cup. The top row is simulated without the BFECC in velocity advection, where the cup fails to tumble. The bottom row is simulated with BFECC and the cup tumbles thanks to the reduced damping in velocity field.
        
      
      
        <H1>References</H1>
        
          [ABS96] A LMGREN A. S., B ELL J. B., S ZYMCZAK W. G.: A numerical method for the incompressible navier-stokes equations based on an approximate projection. SIAM Journal of Scientific Computing 17, 2 (March 1996).
          [CMT04] C ARLSON M., M UCHA P. J., T URK G.: Rigid fluid: Animating the interplay between rigid bodies and fluid. In SIGGRAPH (2004), ACM.
          [DL03] D UPONT T. F., L IU Y.: Back and forth error compensation and correction methods for removing errors induced by uneven gradients of the level set function. Journal of Computational Physics 190, 1 (2003), 311–324.
          [DL04] D UPONT T. F., L IU Y.: Back and forth error compensation and correction methods for semi-lagrangian schemes with application to interface computation using level set method. In CDSNS2004-399, School of Mathematics, Georgia Institute of Technology (2004).
          [ELF05] E NRIGHT D., L OSASSO F., F EDKIW R.: A fast and accurate semi-lagrangian particle level set method. Computers and Structures 83 (2005), 479–490.
          [EMF02] E NRIGHT D., M ARSCHNER S., F EDKIW R.: Animation and rendering of complex water surfaces. In SIGGRAPH (2002), ACM.
          [FF01] F OSTER N., F EDKIW R.: Practical animation of liquids. In SIGGRAPH (2001), ACM, pp. 15–22.
          [FM96] F OSTER N., M ETAXAS D.: Realistic animation of liquids. Graphical Models and Image Processing 58, 5 (1996), 471– 483.
          [FSJ01] F EDKIW R., S TAM J., J ENSEN H.: Visual simulation of smoke. In SIGGRAPH (2001), ACM, pp. 23–30.
          [HK03] H ONG J.-M., K IM C.-H.: Animation of bubbles in liquid. In EUROGRAPHICS (2003), vol. 22.
          [HKLS04] H AARIO H., K OROTKAYA Z., L UUKKA P., S MO LIANSKI A.: Computational modelling of complex phenomena in bubble dynamics: Vortex shedding and bubble swarms. In Proceedings of ECCOMAS 2004 (2004).
          [JEH02] J OBARD B., E RLEBACHER G., H USSAINI M. Y.: Lagrangian-eulerian advection of noise and dye textures for unsteady flow visualization. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 8, 3 (2002).
          [OKBG00] O EVERMANN M., K LEIN R., B ERGER M., G OOD MAN J.: A Projection Method for Two-Phase Incompressible Flow with Surface Tension and Sharp Interface Resolution. Tech. Rep. ZIB-Report 00-17, Konrad-Zuse-Zentrum für Informationstechnik Berlin, 2000.
          [OS88] O SHER S., S ETHIAN J. A.: Fronts propagating with curvature-dependent speed: Algorithms based on hamiltonjacobi formulations. Journal of Computational Physics 79 (1988), 12–49.
          [SAB ∗ 99] S USSMAN M., A LMGREN A., B ELL J., C OLELLA P., H OWELL L., W ELCOME M.: An adaptive level set approach for incompressible two-phase flow. Journal of Computational Physics 148 (1999), 81–124.
          [SSK05] S ONG O., S HIN H., K O H.: Stable but nondissipative water. ACM Transactions on Graphics 24, 1 (2005), 81–97.
          [SSO94] S USSMAN M., S MEREKA P., O SHER S.: A levelset approach for computing solutions to incompressible two-phase flow. Journal of Computational Physics 114, 1 (1994), 146–159.
          [Sta99] S TAM J.: Stable fluids. In SIGGRAPH (1999), ACM, pp. 121–128.
          [TFK ∗ 03] T AKAHASHI T., F UJII H., K UNIMATSU A., H IWADA K., S AITO T., T ANAKA K., U EKI H.: Realistic animation of fluid with splash and foam. In EUROGRAPHICS (2003), vol. 22.
          [Wei04] W EISKOPF D.: Dye advection without the blur: A levelset approach for texture-based visualization of unsteady flow. In EUROGRAPHICS (2004), vol. 23.
        
        c The Eurographics Association 2005.
      
    
  

</Document>
